好的，
All right,
欢迎学习 6.S081 操作系统，
welcome to 6.S081 operating systems,
我是 Robert ，我将和 Frans 一起执教，
I'm Robert I'll be co-lecturing
另外， David 和 Nicolass 作为
with Frans and David and Nicolaas
助教。
of the TAs.
在 zoom 讲座的时候，
So, please during the zoom lectures,
随时可以提问，
ask questions,
你可以讲话打断我，
you can either interrupt me by
或者在聊天窗口中
audio or enter something into
输入一些东西。
the chat window.
我们会有一名工作人员查看
Um, one of the staff will see and ask
question for you.
并替你提问。
顺便说一下，我们会录下这些讲座，
By the way we'll be recording these
然后把录音开放出来，
lectures and then we'll post recordings later
这样你们可以复习，
so you can review them or for
people who can't make this time so
或者对于这次来不了的人，
they can nevertheless see lectures.
他们仍然可以看到讲座。
好的，首先我想列出
All right, I want to start by
课程的一些目标。
laying out some of the goals
那么，
of the course. So,
第一个是，
number one is to um,
understand a design and implementation
理解操作系统的
of operating systems.
设计和实现。
嗯，
Um,
设计是一种高层次的结构，
design is sort of high level structure
而实现实际上是代码
and implementation is really about what the
看起来的样子，
code looks like,
我们将花费大量的时间在这两个方面。
and we'll spending a lot of time with both.
为了更深入地理解
And in the interest of getting a
deep understanding of what's going on,
这些怎么运行，
you'll get hands-on experience with a small
你将获得实践经验，通过使用
一个小型操作系统，
um, a small operating system,
xv6 操作系统。
the xv6 operating system.
嗯，
Um, and,
除了实际查看
in addition to actually looking at an
现有的操作系统，
existing operating system,
在实验室中，你还可以
you'll be a in the labs
获得以下经验，扩展操作系统，
get a bunch of experience extending
改进操作系统，
the operating system modifying improving its
编写使用操作系统接口的
behavior and writing system software that
系统软件，
it uses the operating system interfaces,
在操作系统运行应用程序时。
if it works an application.
嗯，
Um,
这就是你们
so this is what you're going to
在课程中要做的。
be doing in the course.
Um,
在课程中，我们对操作系统
We're also interested in what the purpose
本身的用途
of the operating system itself is as
也很感兴趣。
well as the course.
因此，
So for that I have a
我有一系列
sort of list of a couple
的东西，
of things which,
你知道的，有很多操作系统，
um, you know there's lots of operating system,
不同的操作系统，
different operating systems out there,
它们通常有一套共同的用途.
they typically have a common set of purposes.
其中一个就是对硬件的抽象，
Um, one of them is to abstract the hardware,
就是通常
um, that is what you're given
你的起点，
typically as a kind of starting point is
就是买一台电脑，
you buy a computer,
一台电脑有 CPU 和内存，
a computer has a CPU and memory
但是这是一个非常低的层级。
but that's a very low level.
作为一组资源，
A set of resources,
拥有更高级别的接口
it's fantastic to have a much higher
和抽象是非常棒的，
level interfaces and abstractions that applications can
应用程序可以使用这些接口和抽象，
use such as processes or file systems
例如为了方便和可移植性而使用进程或文件系统。
both for convenience and for portability.
操作系统的另一个非常重要的任务是
Another very important task of an operating
在许多应用程序中
system is to multiplex the hardware
复用硬件。
among many applications.
你可能正在运行文本编辑器和
Um, you might be running a text editor,
编译器，
and a compiler,
或者可能
or maybe
在您的操作系统上运行
a multiple different database servers or something
多个不同的数据库服务器或其他东西，
on your operating system,
这非常棒，能够让
it's fantastic to be able to have
操作系统
the operating system run
同时运行，
both of them at the same
或者所有的事情
time or all the things are
都在同一时间进行，
going on at the same time
而不会受到干扰。
without having them interfere.
这通常被称为多路复用，
That's often called multiplexing, because
因为操作系统中
there may be a lot of
可能会同时
things happening in the operating system
发生很多事情，
at the same time, it's critical
关键是即使有 bug ，
that they not interfere unintentionally,
它们也不会无意中干扰，
even if they have bugs and that's
这就是所谓的隔离任务。
a task is called isolation.
不同的活动
the idea that,
不应该
a different activities should not be allowed
互相干涉。另一方面，
to interfere. On the other hand,
有时不同的活动
there are times when different activities would
可能需要互相干扰、
like to interfere,
交互或协作，
would like to interact or cooperate,
例如，如果我
so for example if I create a
使用编辑器创建了一个文件，
file with a text editor,
我希望编译器可以读取该文件，
and I'd like my compiler to read
我们肯定希望
the file and we definitely want to
允许这种共享。
allow that kind of sharing.
所以我们想允许分享，
Um, so we wanna allow sharing [minutes],
像用户想的那样。
um，sort of what the user has in mind.
但是在很多情况下，
But in many circumstances,
用户不想分享，
user doesn't want sharing maybe
可能你登录了像 Athena 这样的
you're logged into a time sharing
分时处理服务器，
machine like Athena,
你不想别人看到
and you don't want other people to
你的文件，
read your files,
所以需要的时候，我们分享，
um, so we also need as well sharing
而不需要的时候，
we want, to not share when we
我们不分享。
don't want to um.
我们可以称其为安全系统或
Which we could call security or a
权限系统，即访问控制系统。
permission system an access control system.
人们看重操作系统的
Another thing that people value in operating
另一个原因是，
systems is if you spend a lot
如果你为一台计算机的硬件上花了很多钱，
of money on the hardware on a
你希望应用程序
computer you'd like your application to be
能够获得硬件
able to get a sort of full
能够提供的全部性能。
performance that a hardware ought to be
而且，
able to provide. And,
很多都是应用编程，
a lot of that is just application programming,
但是，
um, but,
不可避免的，
um inevitably,
不幸的是，其中一些问题是
unfortunately, some of it is the operating system
操作系统必须确保它提供的任何服务
has to make sure that whatever services
都不会阻碍
it provides don't get in the way
应用程序获得高性能，
of applications getting high performance,
所以你希望至少
so you want to at least not
不要阻碍，
get in the way and maybe even
甚至可能帮助应用程序
help applications achieve
获得良好的性能。
good performance.
嗯，最终。
Um, finally.
TODO:
由于大多数操作系统必须支持
With most operating systems have to support
广泛的不同应用程序，
a wide range of different applications,
可能是笔记本电脑运行编辑器，
maybe it's a laptop running a text editor,
可能是运行游戏，
maybe it's running games,
可能是您的操作系统需要支持
maybe your operating system needs to support
数据库服务器或云计算，
database servers or cloud computation,
通常因为操作系统的设计和构建
and usually because operating systems are quite
成本很高，
expensive to design and build, people use
所以人们使用相同的操作系统来执行许多不同的任务，
the same operating systems for many different
例如 Linux，
tasks like Linux,
在我提到的所有情况下，我相信
for example which I'm sure many of
你们中的许多人都在
you are running a is used in
运行相同的操作系统，
all of the situations I mentioned so
因此相同的操作系统
the same operating system really has to
必须能够支持一系列，
be able to support a range of,
通常是非常不同的用途。
um, often quite different uses.
所以我们希望能够
So we're hoping to be able
同时支持
to support sort of all these
所有这些不同的目标。
different goals simultaneously.
在课程中，我们将听到
And we'll hear more about all of
更多关于这些的信息。
them during the course.
好的，
All right,
操作系统，
um, operating systems,
几十年来人们总结出
so people worked out a
一套设计思想，
set of design ideas over the decades
它们以一种很好的方式
have worked pretty well sort of ways
组织事情。
of organizing things.
我来给你们展示一下
I'm going to lay out for you,
这种经典设计。
this sort of classic.
这是这门课的的
A organization sort of standard deal for, um,
标准组织方式，
this course and,
其实在很多操作系统上
um, is actually quite common around
都是很常见的。
for many operating systems.
这是一种操作系统内部组织，
So this is sort of OS internal organization, or，
或者，在我看来，
The way I think about it
用这个方形
is in terms of a box
表示计算机，
for the computer,
计算机
the computer sort of
附带了一堆硬件，
comes with a bunch of hardware resources,
我把它们放在下面，
which I'll put at the bottom,
有 CPU 、内存、存储的磁盘，
maybe their CPU and ram, disk for
网络接口，
storage and maybe a network interface,
这些硬件，
this sort of hardware,
是最低的一层。
that's the lowest layer.
在顶部，你想要
So at the top you want to
运行各种应用程序，
run various applications,
也许是一个文本编辑器，
maybe a text editor I have use
我使用 VI ，
VI as a text editor,
如果你要运行 C 编译器 CC，
if you're going to run a C compiler CC,
如果你要运行很多其他的东西，
you know if you run lots of
我们今天会讲很多
other things we're gonna talk a lot
关于 Shell 的东西，
today about the Shell which is the,
它是命令行界面，
um, command line interface,
所以我们有所有这些不同的程序
so we have all these different programs
在运行。
that are running.
这里是应用程序运行的地方，
Um, and this is the sort of world
通常被称为
in which a applications run is usually
用户空间。
called user space.
与此截然不同的是，
Um, and as distinct from that there's
这里有一个程序，
a single program,
一个特殊的程序，
a special program,
它一直在运行，叫做内核，
that's always running called the kernel and
内核是计算机资源的
the kernel is sort of the guardian
守护者，
of the resources of the computer,
它在你第一次开机时启动，
it's what first boots up you turn on the computer,
只有一个，管理数据，
um, there's just one of it maintains data,
帮助管理这些进程和
um. To help manage each of these processes
内核也有大量的数据结构
and the kernel also means lots of
data structures to help interface and,
来帮助接口和
um, all the different kinds of hardware.
所有不同种类的硬件。
这些用户程序需要使用服务，
Um, these user programs need to use,
内核也内置了
the kernel also has built in
很多服务。
a bunch of services.
嗯，
Um，
举个例子，通常有一个文件系统。
for example a there's typically a file system
在内核内实现，它实现了
implementation inside the kernel that implements things
文件名、文件内容和
like file names and file contents and
目录，并且了解如何
directories and understands how to store the
将文件存储在磁盘中，
files in the disk,
因此你的程序
so your programs are going to talk
访问内核中的文件，
to the files inside the kernel and
而文件系统
file system implementations is going to
访问磁盘。
talk to the disk.
在这门课上，
In this course,
我们主要关注的是
Um, where we mostly focus on is all
内核内部发生的所有事情，
the things that has to happen inside
以及用户程序和内核
the kernel and on the interfaces
之间的接口。
between user programs and the kernel.
还有内核里面的
As well as the structure of the software,
软件结构。
um, inside the kernel.
所以，
So,
我们非常关心内核中的
we care a lot about these services
这些服务。
inside the kernel.
其中之一就是我提到的文件系统，
One of them is a file system I mentioned,
还有
there's also a
对进程的管理，
management of processes,
每个正在运行的程序都称为进程，
each of these running programs is called
它有
the process and it has things like
自己的内存，
its own memory,
还有共享的 CPU 时间。
for example as well as a share of the CPU time. So,
因此，内核将进程作为内核服务
a kernel manages processes
进行管理。
as a kernel service.
嗯，
Um,
内核负责内存的分配，
kernel manages the allocation of the memory,
不同的进程需要
the different processes need different
不同的内存量。
amounts of memory.
内核
The kernel
复用和划分内存，
multiplexes and divides up the memory
在所有不同的进程之间
allocates the memory,
分配内存。
um, among all the different processes.
正如我提到的内核对文件系统的影响，
Um, the kernel as I mentioned a influence
文件系统实际上
the file system, file system really comes
分为三个逻辑部分或
into a three logical or a bunch
一堆逻辑部分，
of logical parts,
但现在我们可以从
but for now we can think of
管理文件内容的角度来考虑它，
it in terms of managing file content,
that's inside files,
也就是在文件内部，
找出在磁盘上的位置。
figuring out where on disk.
每个文件的内容
Each file's content
都是活的，文件系统
ought to live, file system also somewhat
还在某种程度上分开管理一个命名空间，
separately manages a name space that
每个文件都有一个名称，
each file has a name and
有一个层级目录，
there's a hierarchy of directories,
每个目录中都有一堆文件，
every directory has a bunch of
所有这些文件都是
files in it all that's managed
由文件系统管理的。
by the file system.
通常会有某种安全策略，
Um, there's typically some sort of security arrangement,
也可以称为访问控制。
maybe we'll call it access control.
内核决定，
Which the kernel decides that when a
当给定进程想要读取，使用资源时，
given process wants to read, use
可能从读取磁盘，
some resource, maybe read something from the disk,
使用内存，
use some memory,
内核内部的访问控制机制
the access control machinery inside the
可以决定它
kernel is what gets to decide
是允许
yes it's allowed is that
或不允许，
not allowed, that can get pretty
如果涉及到类似 Athena 系统这样的分时系统，
complicated if we're talking about time
可能会变得非常复杂，
sharing systems like Athena systems where
你知道，这些进程中的
there's you know each of these
每个进程都可能
processes may be run by a
由不同的用户运行，
different user and have different access
并对其允许访问的内容
control rules apply to what it's
使用不同的访问控制规则。
allowed to get at.
在一个成熟的操作系统中，
And in a real full-blown operating system
有很多很多
turns out to be many,
其他的服务，
many other services,
你知道，不同的进程
you know there's typically some way for
通常有某种方式相互通信，
different processes to talk to each other
这称为进程间通信，
called inter process communication,
通常有一大堆
there's typically a whole bunch of software
与网络相关的软件，
associated with the network things like the
比如用于网络通信的 TCP/IP 协议。
TCP/IP protocols for talking the network.
通常也会支持声卡，
Um, There's typically support for sound cards there
可能会有数百个不同磁盘和
may be drivers for hundreds of different
数百个不同网卡的驱动程序，
disk and hundreds of different network cards,
所以在一个成熟的操作系统中，
so， in a full-blown operating system is
这里有大量的东西，
a huge amount of stuff here and
这可能会在内核中
this may run to millions of lines
运行数百万行代码。
of code inside the kernel.
这是对内核内部内容的
So, that's sort of a quick overview
概述，
of whats inside the kernel,
我们还对
we're also interested in how applications
应用程序与内核交互
interact with the kernel and what
以及接口定义感兴趣。
that interface looks like.
这个，
The,
一般，
a usual,
这就是内核的 API 。
um, so this is the API for the kernel.
应用程序是如何进入内核，
How applications get at the kernel,
通常是通过 系统调用 来完成的，
a typically that's done with something called
这些看起来
system calls and these are things that
像程序定义的函数调用，
look like function calls that um
但实际上是跳入内核，
programs can make, but actually jump into
在内核中执行
the kernel and execute a system call
系统调用实现，
implementation in the kernel,
在这节课的后半部分，
I'll talk a bunch about that
谈到这些。
in the latter part of this
现在，我只想
lecture. For now just to give
让你初步了解一下，
you a flavor here,
应用程序代码中
what a couple of different system calls
几个不同的系统调用
might look like in the source code
是什么样子。
of an application.
一种可能是，
One might be that if you want
如果一个应用程序想要打开文件，
an application wants to open a file,
它会调用 open 系统调用。
and it calls the open system call.
把文件名传给
And tells the open system called the
open 系统调用，
name of the file,
可能想要打开
so maybe it wants to open a
一个名为 out 的文件并写入，
file for writing called "out" and the
本例中，
next argument here saying 1
下一个参数是 1 。
in this case. I want to
我想写那个文件，
write that file,
所以这个看起来像函数调用。
and so this thing that looks like a function call.
open 系统调用，
It opens the system calls actually special
实际上是跳入内核的特殊代码，
code that jumps into the kernel and
内核获得这些参数，
the kernel can retrieve these arguments executes
执行一些实现 open 的内核代码，
some kernel code that implements open,
可能会访问磁盘，
maybe talks to the disk,
然后返回一个值，
and then returns a value and that's
这就是文件描述符，
this file descriptor,
fd 表示文件描述符。
as fd stands for file descriptor.
程序可以
Um, which is the program can
使用文件描述符
then use as a handle to
来访问这个打开的文件。
refer to this open file.
如果你想写一个文件，
Um, if you want to write to a file,
使用的
the system call did,
系统调用是 write ，
to do that is called write,
你必须向它传递一个文件描述符，
you have to pass it one
这个描述符与 open
of these file descriptors the same as
返回的文件描述符相同。
was returned by open.
这些是系统调用中
Um, these are arguments that are passed in
传递的参数。
the system call.
从程序到内核，
From the program into the kernel,
你给它一个指针，
and you give it a pointer,
指向一个字符缓冲区，
to a buffer of characters so an
在 C 语言中，
easy way to do that in the
一个简单的方法是，
C programming language,
这个例子
which these examples are written by as
使用双引号，
double quotes then,
然后是字符串，
um, the string,
字符串中的 '\n'
the bytes of the string '\n'
表示换行，
is a new line and the third
第三个参数是字符数。
argument is the count of characters.
如果你想写入，这里是重点，
Um, if you want to write so this really gets point,
把内存里的这个地址传过去。
pass this address in memory.
你在告诉内核，
So you're telling the kernel, look,
请把这个地址的 6 个字节
please write 6 bytes from this
写到这个文件描述符
address to the file that this
关联的文件中。
file descriptor refers to.
一个更有意思的系统调用是
A much more exciting system call
fork 系统调用，
the encounter is the fork system
fork 可以
call, fork is the system call
创建一个新进程，
that creates a new process,
返回创建一个
um, and returns actually creates a process that's
与调用方相同的进程，
identical to the caller and fork returns
fork 返回标识符，即进程标识符 pid ，
the identifier the process identifier pid,
新进程比[那]
um, new process is more
复杂得多。
complicated than [that].
我们还会听到更多关于这方面的内容。
We'll hear more about this.
同样，
So again,
这些看起来像函数调用，
these are all look like function calls,
但是系统调用很特殊，
but the system calls are special because
因为它们跳入内核。
they jump into the kernel.
这是初步了解，
Um, that's taste,
稍后我们会看到更多。
we'll see more later.
这是一个快速的概述。
That is a sort of quick overview,
嗯。
Um, I wanna.
再提一下为什么我发现
Just mention why I find a operating
操作系统的学习，
the study of operating systems,
既有挑战性，又十分有趣。
to be both a challenging and interesting.
为什么它值得
Why you know why it's maybe worth
得在这方面开一门课。
um, intellectually worth taking a course in this area.
这很难的一个原因是环境是难以应对的，
So, one reason why it's hard is that
内核的编程环境是难以应对的，
the environment is unforgiving, programming environment
因为当你在编程时，
inside the kernels unforgiving, because you're,
当你修改内核或
your when you're programming when you're modifying
扩展内核
the kernel or extending the kernel of
编写新的操作系统内核时，
writing a new operating system kernel,
你提供的是其他人
you're providing the infrastructure that everybody
认为已经存在的基础设施
else assumes is already present to
来运行他们的程序。
run their programs.
每个人在编写普通应用程序时
And then everybody else gets an operating
在他们的程序下
system under their program when they write
都有一个操作系统，
ordinary application programs,
但当我们构建操作系统时，
but when we build operating systems
操作系统下
what we get is the hardware
直接是硬件，
underneath our operating system which turns
结果是更难处理。
out to be more difficult to
在这个课程当中，
deal with. In this course,
我们
we, um,
我们用到一个叫 QEMU 的硬件模拟器，
we get to use a hardware simulator called QEMU,
你，
um, you,
它模拟一个 CPU 和一台计算机，
um. That simulates a CPU and a computer
这样做会好一点，
and that makes a little bit better,
但它仍然是困难的
but it's still a kind of a difficult
环境编程。
um, environment programming.
困难又有趣的
Another reason why it's hard and
另一个原因是，
interesting is because if you're designing
如果你在设计操作系统，
operating system,
就必须满足一系列矛盾。
you have to satisfy a bunch of tensions.
这需要真正的设计思想，
Um that require real design thought,
其中之一就是
so one is that you'd like your
你希望你的操作系统要有效率。
operating system to be both efficient.
这通常意味着它在
Um, which often means that it operates at
接近硬件的低层上运行，
a low level close to the hardware,
但是为了便于使用，
but for ease of use,
而且因为现实生活中的人
and because real live people have to
必须使用你的操作系统编写程序，
write programs that use your operating system,
所以我们希望它
we'd like it also to be a
也是一个正确的高层次抽象。
right abstract high-level.
一个可移植的接口，
A portable interfaces and it's a
提供一个简单的抽象接口
neat trick to provide a abstract
需要巧妙的技巧。
interfaces that are simple.
便携的，但也很有效率的。
A portable but they are also efficient.
另外一个矛盾就是
Um, another tension is that we'd like to
我们要提供一个非常强大的操作系统服务，
provide a very powerful operating system services
让操作系统可以承担
so that the operating system can shoulder
很多负担。
a lot of the burden.
运行程序像
Um, running programs like a powerful
强大的操作系统服务。
operating system services.
但是
Um, but,
我们也希望有简单的接口。
we also want to have simple interfaces.
我们不想让程序员
Um that we don't want a
使用一个非常复杂、难以理解的接口，
tremendously complex hard to understand interfaces
因为
for programmers to use because I'm
我不会去理解它们，
not going to understand them,
他们可能会发现很难使用。
and they may find it hard to use.
所以这是一个非常简单的 API ，
Um, so this is really simple API,
可以提供
and so this is possible to do
一个简单的接口，
to provide a simple interfaces that have
里面有一个强大的机器，
powerful a machinery inside them will always
这一直在寻找。
be searching for.
简单的接口提供了
Sort of simple interfaces provide
强大的服务。
a powerful services.
嗨， Robert ，有人提问。
Hey, Robbery, we've got a question in the chat.
系统调用跳入内核
Um, what is unique/different about saying
有什么独特/不同之处，
system calls jump into the kernel i.e
与跳转到另一个函数的
as opposed to a standard function call
标准函数调用相比。
that jumps to another function.
好的，
Um, well,
内核是
the kernel has, the kernels is,
一段始终驻留的代码
um, a piece of code that's always resident
并且具有特权，
that has special privileges that were that
因为内核在机器启动时加载，
because it booted the machine booted the
内核具有特权，
kernel a kernel has special privileges,
它可以直接访问各种硬件，
it can get directly at all kinds
比如普通用户程序
of hardware like the disk device that
无法访问的磁盘设备，
ordinary user programs,
所以如果你执行
can't get at, so if you make
一个普通函数调用。
a an ordinary function call,
你调用的函数没有
um, the function your calling doesn't get it
获得任何关于硬件的特权，
doesn't get any special privileges with respect
而如果你对内核
to the hardware whereas if you make
执行系统调用，
a system call into the kernel, we'll
后面我们会详细谈论这是如何工作的，
talk about how this works,
但这就像当系统调用
but that ends up as when it
跳到内核时，
jumps into when the system call jumps
内核中的系统调用实现
into the kernel a system call implementation
获得了所有这些特权，
in the kernel then gets all these
这样它就可以修改
special privileges so that it can modify
各种敏感的和受保护的
all kinds of sensitive and protected,
硬件资源，
um, hardware resources like for example getting
例如直接访问硬盘。
directly at the hard disk.
我们稍后会看到更多关于这一切的细节。
Um, we'll see a lot more detail for all this shortly.
好的，我们要说的最后一个矛盾是，
Okay, so a final tension that we
所有的操作系统都需要满足你的要求，
want that all operating systems need
你会给程序带来
to satisfy your gonna give programs
尽可能多的灵活性，
as much flexibility as you can
你不想限制它们，
you don't want to constrain them,
所以你想要有很强的灵活性。
so you want to have very flexible.
接口，
Um. Interfaces,
但是确实需要在一定程度上约束程序，
but you do need to constrain program
因为你绝对必须有
somewhat because you absolutely have to have
一些安全概念。
some notion of security.
我们喜欢程序，程序是很自由的，
We love for programs programs complete freedom
但它不可能是完全的自由，
but it can't be complete can't be
不可能真正的完全自由，
really complete because we don't want programs
因为我们不想让程序直接访问硬件，
to get directly at the hardware or
或者干扰其他程序，
to interfere with other programs or a
或者某种程度上
sort of be able to interfere with
干扰操作系统本身的操作。
the operation of the operating system itself.
那么，
Um, so,
这些就是你需要知道的。
these are all you know.
做好这项工作是可能的，
It's possible to do a good job
我们将对此进行大量讨论，
and we'll talk a lot about it
但是在这两列中
but it's always a bit of a
同时提供这两个属性
puzzle to provide sort of both of
总是有点令人费解的。
these properties in both of these columns.
另一个让操作系统设计
Another thing that makes OS design hard
变得困难和有趣的事情是，
and interesting is that operating systems provide
操作系统提供了很多功能和服务，
a lot of features and a lot
但它们实际上倾向于交互，
of services but they actually tend to
有时会以奇怪的方式进行交互，
interact and sometimes in odd ways that
这需要很多思考，
require a lot of thought so even
即使是我给出的简单示例。
the simple examples I gave.
用 open 和 fork ，
Um, with open and fork,
这两个交互，
those two interact actually if a program,
实际上如果是一个程序使用 open 系统调用
um, allocates a file descriptor with the
分配文件描述符，
open system call,
然后分配相同的程序，
and then that same program,
就是 fork 。
um, fork.
fork 的语义是，
Um, and the semantics of fork just
你创建了
turned out to be that you
一个新进程，
create a new process that's a
它是当前进程的副本，
copy of the current process,
你打开了
this file descriptor,
这个文件描述符
you opened.
这是一个副本，
If that's truly to be a copy,
这个文件描述符
this file descriptor still has to be
仍然在孩子中存在并可用，
present and usable in the child and,
所以必须仔细考虑，
and so that has to be thought
这就是文件，
through that is the files,
打开的文件描述符
the opened file descriptors interact with fork
以这种方式与 fork 交互，
in this interesting way and somebody has
必须找到一个能让子进程
to figure out a should the child
读到的文件描述符。
be able to get at.
在调用 fork 之前
The file descriptors created before fork
创建的文件描述符，
is called and the answer has
答案是肯定的，
to be yes,
也就是我们要看的操作系统。
the operating systems we're going to look at.
好的，
Um. All right, so other things
其他有趣的事情
that are turned out to
我已经提过了，
be interesting I already mentioned
操作系统必须满足
that operating systems have to
各种各样的用途，
cater to a wide variety
就像数据库服务器
of uses the same OS
和智能手机
used both for database servers
使用相同的操作系统，
and smartphones,
操作系统。
for example. And operating systems,
随着时间的推移，
as time goes on the hardware
你运行的硬件，
that you run, hardware
你得到的硬件，
you get,
典型的计算机会发生变化，
but typical computers changes,
可能会得到超高速的固态硬盘存储，
maybe get superfast ssd storage instead of
而不是机械硬盘。
mechanical hard drive.
例如，
For example,
大约 15 年前，
about fifteen years ago multi
多核计算机
core computers went from being rare
从稀有的发展到无处不在，
curiosities to being pervasive and and
最近我们看到了数量级的提速和
recently we've seen order of magnitude
网络运行的速度，
speedups and how fast networks operate
所有这些都需要重新思考。
and so all these require rethinks.
嗯，
Um,
会定期介绍操作系统是怎么设计的。
periodically of how operating systems are designed.
这些就是
Now so so those are those are
为什么你可能会选择这门课程的原因，
sort of intellectually why you might take
还有一些更实际的原因，
the course there's also some more practical
你可能会很高兴
reasons why you might be glad to
选修这门课程，
have taken this course,
一个是如果你对
one is if you're interested in what
计算机内部发生的事情感兴趣，
happens inside computers,
想知道并
what goes on and saw under the
探寻计算机内部的秘密，
hood a sort of in secret,
当你打开你的计算机时，
when you turn on your computer,
这是一个很好的课程，
um, this is a good course to take,
类似地，如果你喜欢基础设施，
similarly if you like infrastructure that
也就是如果你喜欢
is if if you enjoy building
建立一种其他程序
a sort of services that other
可以使用的服务。
programs can then use them.
当然，这基本上都是
This is of course essentially all
关于基础设施的，
about infrastructure because that's that's what
因为这就是操作系统。
operating systems are.
如果你曾经
If you ever need to
花费大量时间
spend a lot of time
来跟踪应用程序代码中的 bug 或
tracking down bugs in application
跟踪安全问题，
code or tracking down security
通常这涉及到
problems often that involves understanding
了解操作系统内部
what was going on inside
发生了什么，
the operating system because it's
因为最终是操作系统
ultimately the operating system that
实施了很多安全措施，
enforces a lot of security
当出现问题时，
and when things go wrong,
是操作系统必须收拾残局，
it's the operating system has to pick
因此通常涉及到
up the pieces so that's often involved
跟踪 bug ，最后是操作系统。
in tracking down bugs, and finally.
有两个提问。
Two more questions from the chat,
第一个问题是，
so the first is how important
对于应用程序开发人员来说，
is it for application developers to
真正深入了解开发应用程序的
truly deeply understand the operating systems
操作系统有多重要，
of developing their applications for do
他们是否需要成为专家。
they necessarily need to be experts.
你不必是专家，
You don't have to be an expert,
但是如果你花费大量时间
but if you spend a lot of
开发、维护和调试应用程序，
time developing and maintaining and debugging applications,
最终会对操作系统
you'll eventually end up knowing a lot
有很多了解，
about the operating system,
不管你
whether you,
是不是有意或无意，
whether you meant to or not just,
它就这样出现了，
it just comes up and you're often
你经常被迫理解它。
forced to understand.
第二个问题是，
Um. And the second question is do
像 Python 这样的高级编程语言
high-level programming languages like python use
是否直接使用系统调用，
system calls directly are there built
为了方便，编写了内置的包装器。
in slash wrappers for convenience.
很多高级语言
A lot of high-level languages are sort
在某种程度上是从系统调用中转移出来的，
of at one of move from system calls
这是正确的。
that's absolutely true.
所以，
So, um,
部分原因是
partially because a lot of
许多语言想要提供可移植的，
languages want to provide portable a
可以在
portable environment that works on many
许多不同操作系统上运行，
different operating systems so they can't
因此它们不一定要致力于
necessarily commit to the specific system
任何一种操作系统的特定系统调用。
calls of any one operating system.
所以答案是，
Um, so, the answer,
我想问题是，
the question I think is if you
如果你使用 python ，多少与系统有点隔离。
use python, you're somewhat insulated.
从不是系统调用接口，
From not the system call interface,
你知道 Python 内部当然会做，
you know internally of course python makes,
必须让系统调用来完成它的工作，
has to make system calls get its work done,
嗯，
um, and,
当然，在 Python 和许多其他语言中，
certainly in python and many other languages,
通常有一种方法
there is usually a way to get directly at
可以直接进入系统调用，无论
the system calls whatever your operating system,
你运行的是什么操作系统。
you're running on.
各位同学，
And folks for questions, you can just
你可以自己提问，
feel free to jump in yourself and
不一定需要
ask questions you don't need to go
通过聊天提出问题。
through the chat.
好的，
Okay, Um,
all right,
抱歉。现在我要花几分钟
sorry. I'm going to spend a couple of
讨论 6.S081 的
minutes now talking about class structure
课程结构，
of 6.S081,
然后再回到的技术内容部分。
before switching back to actual technical content.
这有一个课程的网站，
So there is a website for the
我现在不想写出来，
course which I don't want to write
但是你可以
out just now but it's you
在谷歌上搜索
can find it by looking for
6.S081 找到它。
6.S081 on Google.
而且这个网站，
And the website,
有一个
um, has
课程表，
a schedule,
有课程表上的作业，
it has the assignments on the schedule
还有有实验作业。
that has the lab assignments.
它也有关于课程结构
Um, and it has the sort of
的其他信息，
information about course structure like the
比如它的评分标准。
grading policy on it.
你会想要跟踪另一个
Um, the other big resource you're gonna
重要资源是 piazza 。
wanna keep track of piazza.
我猜，
Um I guess,
每个人都是通过 piazza
everybody was here got here by way
来到这里的，
piazza, um,
但是还有，
but as well as um,
所以我们定期用来做两件主要的事情，
so we used periodically for two main things,
一是让人们能够
one is as a way of people
就实验室作业
being able to ask questions about the
提出问题，
lab assignments and,
工作人员会试着回答这些问题，
a course staff will try to answer these questions,
但你们也完全可以自由地
but you should feel absolutely free to
回答彼此的问题。
answer each other's questions as well. And
在 piazza 上发生的另一件事是，
the other big thing that happens on
如果有公告，
piazza if there's announcements there's any announcements
就会发布在上面。
about the course.
我们会把公告放在 piazza 上，
Um, we'll put the announcement on piazza so
所以你应该关注
you should keep an eye on piazza
piazza 上的公告，
for announcements even if, um,
即使你不用它来寻找实验帮助。
you're not using it for lab help.
这个
Yeah. Um,
the, um,
课程的一个很大的部分当然
one of the big parts of course
就是这些讲座，
is that these lectures,
嗯，
um,
这个讲座会涉及到
lectures will cover basic ideas
基本的理念和操作系统。
and operating systems.
有些课程
Um, some of the lectures will
会详细研究
be devoted to detailed a
xv6 的代码，
study of the code in
这是我们的
xv6 which is
小型教学操作系统，
our small teaching operating system
讨论它是如何工作的，
and so talk about how
我们会在课堂上
it works we'll look at
看代码，
the code and show the
并演示代码的执行过程，
code executing during lectures,
另外，在很多课程之前，
and in addition before many of
我们会先做作业，
the lectures, we'll be assignments reading
阅读书中的作业，
assignments from a book that sort
这本书描述了 xv6 是如何运行的，
of describes how xv6 operates and
以及为什么它是这样设计的。
why it's designed that way.
所以你应该在上课前做阅读，
So you do the readings before the
这样就能听懂
class so they understand the discussion
课堂上的讨论，
in the class,
一些课程专门讲授背景知识，
some of the lectures are devoted to
帮助你做实验。
background to help you do the labs.
像 C 语言是如何工作的，
Um, so like about C works of how
RISC-V，也就是我们要使用的
the RISC-V, which is the microprocessor
微处理器。
that we'll be using.
你们会发现这对理解
Um that you'll find helpful in understanding
如何做实验很有帮助，
how to do the labs and towards
在课程接近尾声的时候，
the end of the course,
我们会用一些课，
we'll spend some lectures discussing some
讨论一些操作系统论文，
operating system papers,
研究论文，和该领域的一些经典论文，
research papers and some classic papers in
会要求你们在讲课前
the field which you will ask that
阅读这些论文，
you read before the lecture and then
然后我们会在课程中讨论这些论文。
we'll sort of talk about the papers
所有的讲座，
during the lecture. For all the lectures
几乎所有的讲座，
are almost all the lectures,
我们要求你在
we ask that you submit a question
讲座之前，
about the reading,
为讲座提交
um for the lecture before the actual
一个关于说读文章的问题。
time of the lecture which.
你们中的许多人或所有人
Many or all of you did for
都参加了这次讲座，谢谢你们，
this lecture for which thank you,
我们会查看这些问题来帮助我们。
um, and we will read those questions to help us.
指导我们讨论什么，
Guide us about what to talk about
我们会尽力回答
and we'll try to answer as many
尽可能多的问题，
of the questions as we can,
尽管很少有时间，
although there's rarely time,
不过，我们没有时间回答所有问题。
unfortunately for us to answer all of them.
课程的下一个重要部分是实验。
Um, the next big part of the course of the labs.
几乎每周都有
There's a programming lab do,
一个编程实验，
um, almost every week and the point of
这个实验的目的是
the labs is to help you get
帮助你亲身体验，
hands on experience with,
实现和使用操作系统。
implementing and using operating systems.
下周到期的一个实验
A lab that's due next week is
实际上是关于如何编写应用程序，
actually about using about writing applications that
这些应用程序用到的系统调用
make the call the system calls will
随后将会讨论。
be talking about.
与此之后的
Whereas most of those labs after
大多数实验不同，
that are involved,
要么实现基本的操作系统功能，
you either implementing basic operating system
要么
features or adding
向 xv6 操作系统
a kernel extensions to the xv6
添加内核扩展，
operating system,
最后一个实验，
the very last lab and one in
是实际添加网络堆栈和
which you actually add a network stack
网络驱动程序的实验，
and a network driver so you'll be
以便能够通过网络连接
able to connect in over the network
到你运行的操作系统。
to the operating system that you run.
你应该，
You should,
如果你对实验有问题，
if you have problems with the lab's
助教会在办公时间提供帮助。
they'll be office hours that,
此外，
TA will hold. In addition
你还可以把问题发布到 piazza 上，
you can post questions to piazza
而且通常可以
and very often you'll be able
比在办公时间更快地
to get useful answers from piazza
得到有用的答案。
more quickly than from office hours.
我们欢迎你讨论实验，
We welcome you discussing the labs
谈论实验，
talking about the labs talking about
讨论如何设计实验解决方案，
how to design the lab solutions
但是我们要求不要
but we ask you please do
看别人的解决方案。
not look at other people's solutions.
重复一遍，你编写的所有代码
Relapse, please all the code you write should
都应该是你自己的，并且你不应该
be your own and you shouldn't share
共享代码或查看其他解决方案。
code or look at other solutions.
评分。当然，
The grading. Of course,
今年我们主要由实验决定，
um. We'll be mostly determined from the labs this year,
所以 70% 的成绩将是，
so 70% of the grade will be,
嗯，
um,
根据你的实验结果，
Um, based on whether or not your lab,
你提交的是否通过测试，我们进行评分，
you submit passes the tests and we for grading,
我们运行的测试与提供给你的测试是相同的，
we run the same tests that we
所以如果你的实验
supply you so if your lab passes
通过了我们给你的所有测试，
all the tests that we give you
你就可以得到实验的
the chance to show you that full
全部分数。
credit for the lab.
20% 的分数
A 20% of the grade is
来自实验检查会议，
going to be from lab checkoff meetings
你们每个人都将
for each of you will pick a
随机选择几个实验，
couple of randomly selected labs and one
其中一个小组将与你们交谈，
of the teams will talk to you
询问你们关于实现的问题，
and ask you questions about your implementation
以确保你们真的
just to make sure that um,
理解发生了什么。
are you really understand what's going on.
这是实验检查。
It's a lab check offs.
还剩 10% 。
There's a 10% remaining.
很多，有点像
A lot of, kind of
是或不是
be like a yes or no
一或零的事，
one or zero type of thing
或者他们会是，
or would they be,
就像有人会得到，
like could someone get like if they
比如如果他们回答对了一些问题，
answered some of the questions right,
但不是所有的问题
but not all the questions right when
都回答对了，
they get in between,
那么分数是怎样的。
so the grade.
你知道，我还没有想过这件事。
You know I haven't thought this through.
当然有部分学分的情况，
Um, there's certainly room for partial credit
但这不是，
but it's not, it won't
它不会是二进制的，
be binary, it'll definitely be you
你肯定可以获得部分学分。
can receive partial credit.
好吧。最后的 10% 将是由
Okay. Um, the last 10% is going to
家庭作业和
be a driven by the homework and
讲座和 piazza 的参与决定的。
participation during lecture and piazza.
今年不会有考试或
Um. There will be no exams or quizzes,
小测验。
this year.
所以，
Um, and so what,
这意味着大部分的，
that means is that most of the um,
你知道 90% 的成绩是
you know 90% of the grade
由实验决定的。
is being driven by the lab.
所以你应该
So you should,
花很多时间在实验上，
spend a lot of time in the labs,
确保你早点开始，
um, make sure that you start early
有足够的时间完成它们，
and have enough time to complete
解决 bug ，
them and work out bugs in
并获得满分。
order to get full credit.
因此，
And you know as a result of
这将是一门非常实用的
that this is going to be a
面向软件的课程。
very kind of hands-on software oriented course.
还有关于
Any questions about the
课程组织问题吗？
machinery of the course.
嗯，在聊天中有几个问题，
Um, we've got a couple questions in chat,
第一个是组织管理的问题，
so the first is a logistical
目前
question, currently 6.S081
6.S081 没有像往常
isn't listed as usual for the
一样列出来，在系统主修课程中，
system's concentration in the [?],
以后有没有增加课程的计划。
are there plans added to the list
我认为，
of classes later. I think for that
因为它不是批准的高级研究生课程，
because it's not an AAGS
它是高级本科课程，
it's an AUS, it can't be
它不能满足安排要求，
used to fulfill arrange requirements,
它不是研究生水平的课程。
so it's not a graduate level class.
那么，
So, um,
然后我们有唯一的
and then we have is the only
家庭作业来提交问题，
homework to submit questions looking at the
看看日历。
calendar that appears to be the case.
除非我忘了什么。
Unless I'm forgetting something.
我想是这样的，
I think that's the case,
是的。那么，有没有分数比例的情况，
yes. So have, um, are there gonna
像百分之 X 得 A，
be cutoffs for grades like X
百分之 Y 得 B
percent gets an A, Y percent
的情况。
gets a B etc.
不，不，
No no,
嗯，
um,
你知道我们努力
you know we're going to try to
给学生自由。
a free student estimate.
我的评价是
I'm impression of how well you've
你对材料理解得好坏，
understood the material,
并在此基础上给出一个等级，
um, and assign a grade based on that
不会有预先设定的比例。
so there's no predetermined cutoffs.
好的，还有其他的吗。
All right, anything else.
好的。
All right.
对于在聊天中
Just real quick for folks in the
询问主修要求
chat asking about the
的人来说，
concentration requirement, I'm not a hundred
我不是百分之百确定，
percent certain, um,
但 6.S081 不是，
but 6.S081 is not,
它就像是课程获得正式编号之前
it's like a temporary number before the
的一个临时编号，
class gets official one, so it
所以它不会出现在任何地方，
certainly won't be listed anywhere,
如果你需要它来实现主修课程，
if you need it to fulfill a
我想你最好的选择
concentration, I think your best bet is
是填写一份请愿书，
probably to fill out a petition or
给 Katrina Kurtz 他们发邮件。
to email somebody like Katrina Kurtz.
要查看状态是什么，我们无法控制，
To see a what the status is, we don't control,
你知道的，哪些课程
you know what what classes fill these
满足这些要求。
kind of requirements,
这门课将使用什么语言，
unfortunately. And for what language will be using
将使用 C 语言。
the class will be in C.
好的，
Yes, all right,
嗯，
um, Yeah,
好的，对于这堂课的剩下的时间，
All right, for the rest of the lecture
我想谈一下，
I want to talk about how, um,
什么系统调用看起来像应用程序，
what system calls look like applications,
你知道，因为系统调用
um, and you know since the system calls
是操作系统
are the interface to the services that
提供服务的接口，
the operating system provides is actually pretty
所以这些系统看起来是什么样子，
important what those systems look like what
应用程序从系统调用中得到什么，
applications expect from system calls and how
以及它们是如何运行的，
they behave so it's worth understanding what
所以理解接口是什么样子是值得的。
the interface looks like.
你将在第一个实验中
Um, you'll be using the system calls we
使用我们谈到的系统调用，
talk about in the first lab,
并在后续的实验中
um, and extending and improving the implementation
扩展和完善这些系统调用
internal implementation of these system calls
的内部实现。
in subsequent labs.
我们将演示一些程序
What we're gonna do is show some
的简单示例。
simple examples of little programs.
它调用系统调用，我将在 xv6 中为
That call system calls and I'll run
运行它们。
them in xv6 for you.
我将运行它们，
I'm gonna run them,
xv6 是一个，
the xv6 is a, um,
它是一个 unix ，
it's a unix,
一个简化的类 unix 操作系统，
a simplified unix-like operating system unix
unix 是一个古老的操作系统，
is a old operating system that's at
至少作为许多当今的操作系统的基础，
least intellectual basis for many present-day operating
比如 Linux 和 OS X 来说，
systems such as Linux and OS X
它是使用非常广泛的。
it's in very common use.
xv6 我们的教学操作系统
Um, xv6 our teaching operating system is
要简单得多，在某种程度上受到 unix 的启发，
much simpler and sort of inspired by
具有相同的整体结构，
unix and has the same overall structure,
但比任何真正的 unix 操作系统
but is dramatically simpler than any real
都要简单得多。
unix operating system.
它很简单足够，
Um, it's simple enough that hopefully,
你知道，
um, you know it would
你可以在几周内
be relatively straightforward
阅读所有的源代码，
for you to read all the source code,
也可以阅读这本书，
as well as read the book,
当然在本学期，
in a couple of weeks certainly
以便了解
during the semester in order to
xv6 内部发生
kind of understand all of what
的所有事情。
happens inside xv6.
xv6 运行在 RISC-V 处理器上，
Um, xv6 runs on the RISC-V
RISC-V 微处理器，
processor, RISC-V microprocessor and this is
这也是最近 6.004 课程
the same microprocessor that's the focus of
所使用的的微处理器，
recent 6.004
所以你们中的许多人
Um, so many of you may actually
实际上可能对 RISC-V 指令集
know quite a bit about the
有相当多的了解。
RISC-V instruction set.
理论上你可以在 RISC-V 计算机上
Um, in theory you could run xv6
运行 xv6 ，
on top of a RISC-V computer
已经有人这么做了。
and people done that.
但是我们要在 QEMU，
Um, but we're going to run it under the QEMU,
机器仿真器下运行，
um, machine emulator,
只需要把我们得到的写下来。
just write this down we got.
我们的操作系统是 xv6 ，
Our operating system is
运行在 RISC-V
xv6, um, runs on RISC-V
微处理器上，而且不仅是 RISC-V 微处理器，
microprocessor and not just RISC-V microprocessor,
但我们假设周围有
but we assume a certain amount
一定数量的硬件，
of surrounding hardware like memory
比如内存和磁盘。
and disk.
还有 console 界面，让我们可以访问它。
And console interface for us to talk to it.
我们实际上是在 QEMU
Um, We actually run under the QEMU
机器模拟器下运行的。
machine simulator.
这是在 Linux 下运行的，
So that which runs under Linux,
所以实际上这就是你们所能做的一切。
so all you can actually.
在没有硬件的情况下运行 xv6 。
A run xv6 without having that hardware.
好的，现在切换到演示代码。
Okay so kind of switch to a show the code.
好的，
All right,
那么，第一件事是在我的笔记本上安装了 xv6 ，
so, um, first thing is I've a setup xv6 on my laptop,
我要运行它，输入 'make qemu'，
I'm going to run it type 'make qemu',
输入 'make qemu'，
'make qemu',
你会发现自己在实验中
you'll find yourself doing quite a
做了相当多的工作，
bit during the labs,
它编译 xv6 它是用 C 编写的，
um, which compiles xv6 it's written in C,
所以它用 C 编译器
so it's compiled with
编译，
C compiler,
我可能输入 'make clean' 清理一下，
maybe I'll 'make clean' for you,
这样你就可以看到实际的编译过程，
so you can see the actual compilation
我输入 'make qemu' ，
and I might 'make qemu',
它的效果是编译和
which has the effect of compiling and
构建 xv6 内核和
building xv6 kernel and all the
所有用户程序，然后在
user processes and then running them under
QEMU 模拟器上运行。
the QEMU emulator.
在编译过程中会花费一些时间，
Takes a moment around the compiles,
是的，现在我们启动并运行
yeah, and now we're up and running
xv6 和 '$' 提示符，
xv6 and the '$'
你看到的是 shell ，
prompt you see as the shell which
它是 xv6 的命令行界面，
is the command line interface,
仿照 unix上 的shell，
um, to xv6, modeled after the shell on unix,
也是
which is,
如果你登录到 Athena 系统，
um, if you log into Athena organization and
它就像 Athena 你看到的
it's, um, it's like the shell that
那个 shell 。
Athena shows you.
xv6 本身很小，
xv6 itself tiny and it comes with
它附带了一些实用程序，
a small number of utility programs and
例如，我将要运行的 'ls' 程序，
including for example the 'ls' program which
运行 ls ，它给我
I'm about to run run ls and
一个所有文件
it gives me a list of
的列表，
all the files and xv6
xv6 只有二十多个文件，
of which there are only about
包括 grep kill
two dozen including things like grep and
mkdir 和 rm ，
kill and mkdir, rm which
是我们熟悉的
may be familiar to us,
unix 实用程序。
um, as unix utilities.
好的，第一个程序，
Okay, the first program,
我要演示的是
I'm gonna show you to illustrate system
copy 程序，
calls is a program called copy,
嗯，
um,
这里的代码只有一页，
here's the source is just a page,
你在这里看到的程序，
um, so what you're seeing here is
它从第 8 行开始， TODO:
a program that starts on line
main 是 C 语言程序的
8 and main is that sort
一种约定，
of convention for C programs,
它位于第 12 行的循环中，
it sits in a loop at line 12,
然后一次又一次地，
and over and over again, it reads
它读取一些数据作为输入，
some data as input and on line
在第 13 行，然后写入数据，
13 and then writes the data just
只需在第 16 行读取它的输出，
read his output on line 16,
通过运行 copy，
by run copy,
在 xv6 中，它正在等待读取输入，
um, in xv6, it's waiting to read input,
如果我在 xv6 中输入，
if I type some input,
它正在等待读取输入，然后把它返回给我。
reads it and spits it back up to me.
非常简单的程序只做 IO 。
Very simple program just does IO.
就像我提到的，
Um, it's really see as I mentioned a
如果你还不了解 C 语言，
if you don't already know C, it's
这本标准的 C 编程语言书很值得读，
worthwhile getting the standard C programming language
由 Kernighan 和 Ritchie 编写。
book by Kernighan and Ritchie.
我认为课程网站上
And I think there's a
有更完整的参考资料，
more full reference to it on the
它向你们解释了如何用 C 语言编程，
course website which explains to you and,
以及 C 语言最直接的使用方法。
um, very straightforward way how to program in C.
是的，就像我之前提到的，
Yeah, as I mentioned before,
我们甚至写这个程序用了两个，
we even write this program makes two
实际上是三个系统调用，
really three system calls read
read write 和 exit ，我们的系统调用。
write and exit, our system calls.
如果你看一下第 13 行的 read 调用，
Um, if you look at the call to
它有三个参数，
read on line 13, it takes three arguments,
第一个参数是一个文件描述符，
the first argument is a file descriptor
它实际上是对
which is really a reference to a
以前打开的文件的引用。
previously opened file.
shell 确保
Um, and the shell,
当程序默认启动时，
ensures that when a program starts by default,
它的文件描述符 0
it's file descriptor 0 is connected to
连接到控制台输入，
the console input, and its file descriptor
它的文件描述符 1 连接到控制台输出，
1 is connected to the console
这就是为什么我能够
output, and that's why I was
输入到
able to type to
copy 程序并查看输出。
this copy program and see the output.
当然，这些文件描述符是程序预期的，
Um, of course, these file descriptors are expected
这些文件描述符
the program expected these file descriptors have
已经提前打开，
been previously opened and set up by
并由 shell 为其设置。
the shell for it.
0 1 文件描述符，
And 0 1 file descriptors,
是普遍的约定，
pervasive units convention many,
有很多很多 unix 程序希望
many unix programs expect to read from
从文件描述符 1 读取，读取文件描述符 0 ， TODO:
file descriptor 1 and read file descriptor
并写入文件描述符 1 。
0 and write to file descriptor 1.
要读取的第二个参数是
A second argument to read is a
指向某个内存的指针，
pointer to some memory,
程序要求操作系统将数据
um, where the program is asking the operating
读取到
system to read data
内存中的那个地址，
into that address in memory,
这是 buff 参数，
so that's the buff argument and line 10
第 10 行在堆栈上分配 64 字节的内存
allocate 64 bytes of memory on the stack, um,
供 read 读取，
for read to read into, and the
而要读取的第三个参数是程序
third argument to read is the maximum
想要读取的最大字节数，
number of bytes that the program wants
缓冲区的大小
to read and the size of buffs
仅为 60 最大 64 字节， TODO:
as just sixty maximum 64 bytes,
因此 read 调用
so the read call reads up to 64
从连接到文件描述符 0 的任何内容
bytes from whatever is connected to file
读取最多 64 字节，
descriptor 0 and that was
在本例中， 0 这就是我的终端。
my terminal in this example.
read 的返回值
The return value from read it either
可能是
it may be sure of the number
读取的字节数，
of bytes read,
可能是 6 ，
um, which would be 6 and a piece of, um,
输入 "xyzzy" ，
typing "xyzzy" by
可能是从文件中读取的，
be might be reading from a file,
如果到达文件末尾，
if it gets to the end of the file,
就没有更多的字节，
there's no more bytes,
read 将返回 0 。
read will return 0.
如果发生其他错误，
And then some other error occurred like
如文件描述符不存在，
the file descriptor doesn't exist, read may
read 可能返回 -1 。
return -1.
在很多例子中，
And, so in many of these examples
就像在 16 行。 TODO:
like on line 16 there.
我的示例代码没有
Um I don't my example code doesn't
检查系统调用返回是否有错误。
check system call returns for errors.
但是你应该比我更小心，
But you should be more careful than me,
你应该弄清楚
um, um the you should figure out how
系统调用是如何返回错误的，
system calls reflect errors,
通常是返回 -1 ，
it's usually a -1 return
并检查所有系统调用的返回
value and check all system called
是否有错误。
returns for errors.
如果你想知道
And if you want to know
系统调用参数和返回值是什么，
what the system call arguments and
这有一个表格，
return values are, there's a table
我想在书中的第 2 章，
and I think chapter 2 in
解释了所有 xv6
the book explains all of the
系统调用参数和
xv6 system call arguments and
返回值。
return values.
关于 read 系统调用的问题，
The question regarding the read syscall,
如果我们将缓冲区大小的
what if we set the max read
最大读取字节数设置
bytes to size of buff to one
为缓冲区大小加 1 或更大，
plus size of buffer or bigger,
如果我们尝试读取的大小超过该大小会怎样。
so what if we try to read more than the size.
是的，如果有 65 个字节要读取，
Yeah, then if there was 65 bytes to read,
操作系统会很高兴地将
then the operating system would happily will just
这 65 个字节复制到
copy those 65 bytes to
你提供的内存中，
the memory that you provide
当然还有
and of course there's something
堆栈上的其他东西，
else on the stack up
可能是返回程序计数器，
there maybe the return program
或者参数或
counter or an argument or
其他东西，
something and so if you
所以如果你传递 65 个字节，
pass 65,
那么你就是在让内核写垃圾内存。
then you're inviting a kernel to write junk.
放到堆栈上一个意想不到的地方。
Um to an unexpected place in your stack.
因此，这是一个 bug ，
And so that's a bug and it
它可能会导致你的程序崩溃。
may cause your [firm] to crash.
或者做一些其他意想不到的事情，
Or do something else unexpected,
所以作为一个程序员，
so as a programmer,
你在这里必须小心，
you have to be careful here,
没有人用 C 语言
there's nobody writing in C with these
这样使用这些接口。
kind of interfaces there's.
这是非常非常容易编写的代码，
Um, it's very very easy to write
编译器可以通过，
code that the compiler is happy
并且可以运行，
with and will run but absolutely
但绝对是错误的事。
does the wrong thing.
那太糟糕了，但事情就是这样。
Um, so that's too bad but it's the way it is.
好的，
Okay, um,
有一件事需要注意，
one thing to note is that this
这个 copy 程序和 read write
copy program and indeed the read write
系统调用，它们不关心
system calls they don't care about the
数据的格式，
format of data,
他们在读或写，它们只是
they're reading or writing a they just
在这个 copy 程序中
read and write read and write in
读写读写。
this copy program.
处理 8 位字节
Just deal with 8 bit bytes with
用 8 位的流即可。
streams of 8 bit bytes.
如何解释它们完全取决于
Um, how you interpret them is totally up
应用程序，
to the application,
应用程序可能会
so the application maybe,
解析数据记录，作为 C 语言代码，
a parse there data records or as C source code,
或者谁知道是什么。
or who knows what.
操作系统，
The operating system,
只知道这是
um, the only things in terms of a
8 位字节流。
stream of 8 bit bytes.
好的， copy ，
Okay, so copy,
假设这段代码，
assumed this code,
copy ，我可以假设
my copy I can assume that the
文件描述符已经设置好了，
file descriptors are already set up,
但是我们需要有一种方法
but we need to need to have
来创建文件描述符。
a way to create file descriptors.
要做到这一点，最直接的方法就是
And the most straightforward way to do
使用 open 系统调用，
that is with the open system
这是一个名为 open 的程序
call and so here's the source for
的源代码。
a program that called open.
那个，
That um,
我用的是 open 系统调用。
I use the open system call. A
聊天中的提问，
question from the chat,
你说的字节流是什么意思。
what do you mean by a stream of bytes.
我的意思是
Um, I just mean that if a
如果一个文件包含一串字节，
file contains a bunch of bytes,
然后读取
then read then successive spilling a pile
连续一百万个字节的内容，
contains a million bytes,
如果您进行一系列的 read 调用，每个 400
字节。 TODO:
if you make a sequence of read calls each 400 bytes.
你知道，我只读第一个 100 字节，
You know I'll just read the first
然后是第二个 100 字节，
hundred bytes and then the second hundred
然后是第三个，
bytes and then third,
第三个 100 字节。
the third hundred bytes.
嗯。
And um.
好的，
All right,
那么这个程序，
so this program,
open ，我来运行它。
um, called open, I'll run it for you.
它所做的是创建一个
Um, what it does is a opens creates
名为 output.txt 的新文件，
a new file called "output.txt"
然后向其中写入一些字节，
and then write some bytes to it,
我将完成这个操作，
I'm gonna finish this so we don't
我们看不到任何东西，
see anything because it broke data to
因为它将数据放到这个文件中。
this file.
但是我们可以查看
But we can look
它创建的 output.txt 文件，可以看到
this "output.txt" file that created it and see,
"ooo" 写在那里，
um, the "ooo" wrote there,
所以程序中有一个 11 。 TODO:
so an 11 in the program.
进行 open 系统调用，
Makes the open system call,
给它一个文件名 output.txt
give it a filename "output.txt"
和第二个参数中的 "O_" 的选项，
and the "O_" stuff,
open 的标志，
um in the second argument to open
告诉内核中的 open 系统调用实现，
our flags that tell the open system
我们想
call implementation in the kernel, that we'd
用用这个名字创建一个文件，
like to create a file with its
然后写入。
name and we're going to write it.
open 返回新分配的文件描述符。
Open returns a newly allocated file descriptor.
文件描述符只是
Um, and the file descriptor is just
一个很小的数字，
a small number, probably 2 or
可能是 2 3 或 4 这些。
3 or 4 something.
然后我们将相同的文件描述符与
And then we pass that same file
缓冲区一起传递，
descriptor right along with the buffer and
以及多种写入数据的选项，
a number of ways to write a that writes data,
文件，
um, the file,
文件描述符所引用的。
the file descriptor refers to.
文件描述符实际上是
What that file descriptor is actually doing
索引到内核中的一个小表中，
is indexing into a little table inside
内核维护每个进程的状态，
the kernel, the kernel maintains state for each process,
也就是你运行的
that's running each program that you run
每个程序，
and among other things,
内核会记住一个表，
the kernel remembers a table for every
用于按文件描述符索引的每个正在运行的进程，
running process of index by file descriptors
该表可以告诉内核
and the table sort of tells the
每个文件描述符引用的是什么。
kernel what each file descriptor refers to.
好的，关键点是每个进程都有
Okay, a critical point is that each process
自己的文件描述符空间。
has its own sort of space of
因此，
file descriptors. So,
在运行两个不同的进程，
before running two different processes,
两个不同的程序和不同的进程，
two different programs and different processes and
它们都打开一个文件之前，
they both open a file,
它们可能会得到相同的
they may actually get the same number
文件描述符的编号，
back as a file descriptor,
但是因为内核为每个进程维护
but because the kernel maintains a separate
单独的文件描述符，
file descriptor for each process,
所以相同的文件描述符号
the same file descriptor number may refer
在不同进程中可能引用不同文件。
to different files in different processes.
关于这个 open 程序有什么问题。
Any questions that open about this little program.
在聊天中有一个问题，
Now we had a question in
一个不熟悉 C 语言的
chat, question from someone not
人提出的问题，
familiar with C,
这些文件和
how are these files being described different
普通的 C 程序有什么不同，
from normal C programs,
是不是因为我们只使用内核调用，
is it because we're only using kernel
也就是说，我们能不能用 python
calls, i.e couldn't we also open or
打开或写文件。
write a file in python.
嗯，我想我不明白这是
Um, I don't think I understand that
一个 C 程序，
it's a C program,
就是打开和写一个文件。
that's opening and writing a file.
嗯，那会继续下去的。
Um, that's going to move on.
好的，那么你可能
All right so you might ask what
问的是，当……也许问题是，
actually happens when ... Maybe the question
当有人用 C 语言做这件事时，
is when someone is doing it
除了语法，
in C any different than doing
与用 python 有什么不同。
it in Python minus the syntax.
它不是真的，
Well it's not really, um,
当然也有办法，
and, there's certainly ways to, um,
python 提供了很好的函数调用
python provides nice function calls for opening
来打开和做所有这些事情。
and doing all these things too.
或者打开文件，
Or opening files,
比如说在读写文件的时候，
for example in reading writing files,
有一个层级
um, there's a layer of a higher
比较高的函数，
somewhat higher level functions typically not
比如说一般不会有指针
pointers the memory,
指向内存。
for example.
python 为你提供了更多的错误检查。
Um, and python has more error checking for you.
但是当你用 python 打开一个文件，
Um, but when you open a file in
或者用 python 写一个文件的时候，
python or write a file on python, the
你使用的 python 调用，
python calls you make,
归根结底就是这样的系统调用。
boil down to system calls just like these.
这是个好答案吗。
Is that a good answer.
我想是的。
Think so.
好的，
All right,
好的。
all right, um.
我一直在这里讨论，
I've been over here talking to the, um,
xv6 是类似 unix 的 shell ，
xv6 is unix like shell
shell 是人们通常所说的
and the shell is what people often
命令行界面，
call the command line interface,
相对更图形化的用户界面。
um, as opposed to a more graphical user interface.
shell 是，
Um, the shell turns,
如果你没有用过 shell ，
if you haven't used the shell,
shell 对于 unix 系统的
the shell turns out to be a
系统管理来说
pretty useful interface for things like system
是一个非常有用的界面，
management of unix systems,
它提供了很多实用程序
it provides a lot of utilities
来处理文件和
for messing around with files and
程序开发，
for program development and
以及编写脚本来完成所有这些事情。
on writing scripts to do all these
所以，[在继续之前]，
things. So, [some before run],
我想在你输入的时候，
I just want to demonstrate a few
演示几个 shell 常用的功能，
shell features ordinarily when you type things,
你告诉 shell 运行一个程序，
um. You're telling the shell to run a program,
所以当我输入 ls 的时候，
so when I type ls what
意思是
that means is I'm asking the
要求 shell 运行程序，
shell to run the program
程序的名称是 ls ，
whose name is ls, and what
这实际上意味着
that really means is there's a
在文件系统中
file in the file system called
有一个叫做 ls 的文件，
ls that contains some instructions,
它包含一些指令，一些机器指令，
some machine instructions and I'm asking the
我要求 shell 运行
shell to run the instructions that are
文件 ls 中的指令，
in the file called ls,
其中一个 ls ，它的实际作用是， TODO:
one ls now ls what it actually does is, um,
获取当前目录中的
get a listing of the files in
文件列表，
the current directory,
你可以在上面的
and you can see up there
第 4 行看到，
on the 4 line that among
在其他文件中，
the other files that
ls 也是存在的，
ls as exists,
这个列表是一个 TODO:
and this list is a file called
名为 ls 的文件，它实际上
ls which is in fact the file
包含了我刚刚运行的指令。
containing the instructions I just ran.
除了运行程序，
The shell does a few other things
shell 还为你做了其他事情，
for you other than running programs allows
允许重定向 IO ，
you to redirect IO,
例如，如果我输入
so for example if I say
'ls>out' ，意思是
'ls > out' what that means is
要求 shell 运行 ls 命令，
asking the shell run the ls command,
但将其输出重定向到
but with its output redirected to the
名为 out 的文件。
file called out.
我运行 ls 。
I run ls.
我们看不到任何输出，
We don't see any output because the
因为输出都重定向了。
output all went out.
现在我可以出来一堆数据，
Um, now I can out contains a bunch of data,
我们可以，
um, we could,
cat 命令读取一个文件并
The cat command reads a file and
显示该文件的内容，
displays the contents of the file,
我输入 'cat out' 。
so I say 'cat out'.
现在我们来看看，
Just going to see now the now
这和 ls 的输出是相同的。
this is the same output of ls.
你还可以运行
You can also run a command like
像 'grep' 这样的命令，
'grep' and I can give it an
我给它一个参数 "x" 和 'grep x' 。
argument "x" and what 'grep x'.
grep 命令通过模式搜索。
The grep command searches for patterns.
同样，如果我运行 'grep x' ，它将搜索
Again a if I run 'grep x', it's gonna search for
包含 "x" 的输入行。我可以重定向，
lines of input to contain "x". I can redirect,
告诉 shell 将其输入
tell the shell to redirect its input
从文件 "out" 重定向。
from the file "out".
以便查找保存了ls个输出的动作的实例。
In order to look for instances of
acts that saved ls output.
原来有三个文件的名称包含“x”。
It turns out there's three files whose
names contain "x".
嗯。嗯，我们要花一些时间在外壳上，嗯，嗯，它的外壳是一种最传统和最基本的接口单元，因为在Unix最初开发的时候，所有的都是简单的终端接口，就像我们现在使用的那个，单元最初的主要用途是分享时间，让一群人登录到同一台机器上，很像雅典娜和贝壳交谈。
Yeah. Um,
we're going to spend a bunch of
time with the shell,
um, uh,
its shell is sort of the most
traditional and fundamental interface units,
because when unix was first developed, all
there was was simple terminal interfaces,
like the one we're using and
the main use of units originally was
time sharing a bunch of people logging
into the same machine,
much like Athena and talking to shells.
一个关于系统调用和编译器的问题，编译器如何处理生成的系统调用，汇编语言对操作系统定义的某些代码段进行过程调用。
A question about system calls and the compiler,
how does the compiler handles system
calls does assembly generated make a
procedure call to some code segment
defined by the operating system.
嗯，有一个特殊的RISC-V指令，程序可以调用它来转移内核下的控制权，所以实际上当你写C代码让系统叫做open write时，嗯。从技术上讲，实际上是开放的，是C库中的一个C函数。
Um, there's a special RISC-V instruction that
a program can call that transfers control
under the kernel,
so indeed when you write C code
that makes the system called open write,
um. And technically what actually happens is
open is a C function in
the C library.
嗯，但是那个功能里面的指令真的是机器指令，它不是打开的。
Um, but the instructions in that function are
really machine instructions,
it's not open.
我们调用的open函数不是用汇编语言实现的C函数，汇编代码，嗯，由这个叫做eCall的特殊指令组成。
The open function that we're calling isn't
a C function implemented in assembler and,
the assembly code,
um, consists of this special instructions
actually called ecall.
在RISC-V上，将控制权转移到内核的特殊指令，然后内核查看进程、内存和寄存器，以找出参数是什么。
On RISC-V the special instruction
that transfers control
into the kernel,
and then the kernel looks at
the processes memory and registers to
figure out what the
arguments were.
好的，我想看的下一个例子是调用‘fork’的示例程序。
All right, the next example I want
to look at is example program
that calls 'fork'.
创建进程，嗯，这是第12行fork非常简单的用法，我们调用fork，fork所做的是创建调用进程的指令和数据内存的副本，现在我们有两个内存相同的进程。
Creating process,
um, so this is the
very simple use of fork at
line 12, we're calling fork and
what fork does is
creates a copy of the memory of
instructions and data of the calling process,
now we have two processes with identical memory.
fork，则fork系统调用在两个进程中都返回。
Fork, the fork system call returns
in both processes.
在原始进程中，fork系统调用返回进程id，它是一个大于0的整数。
In the original process,
the fork system call returns the process
id which is, um
an integer greater than 0.
对于返回的原始进程，新创建的进程的进程id和在新创建的进程fork中返回0。
The original process for returns,
the process id of the newly created
process and in the newly created process
fork returns 0.
所以我们可以说，即使进程有相同的内存，你也可以通过从fork返回的值来打破新旧进程的对称性。
So we sort of break even though
the processes have identical memory,
you can break the symmetry of
old versus new process by the
return value from fork.
在第16行，您可以看到代码，检查并指出，如果进程id等于0，则必须是子进程，您现在必须在子进程中运行。
And in line 16 you can see code,
the checks and says if the
process id is equal 0 must
be the child,
you must now be running in the child.
嗯，当然另一个进程里面有两个进程，这个调用的进程，通常叫做父进程id大于0。
Um, of course there's two processes in
the other process,
um in the calling process which is
usually called the parent process id is
greater than 0.
嗯，所以孩子会打印“孩子”，家长会打印“家长”。
Um, so the child will print "child" and
the parent will print "parent".
然后他们两个都会离开。所以当我运行fork的时候，现在我们得到了，所以它可能看起来像垃圾。
And then they'll both exit. So when I run fork,
now here we get, so it may look like garbage.
实际上，在分叉之后，这两个进程都在运行，它们都是同时运行的，QEMU实际上为我模拟了一个多核微处理器，所以它们实际上是同时运行的，所以当它们产生输出时。
What's actually happening is that after the fork,
both of these processes are running they're
both running at the same time and
QEMU is actually emulating a multi-core,
microprocessor for me,
so they really are running at
the very same time,
so when they produce output.
它们同时产生输出的每个字节，而另一个进程产生输出的相应字节，所以这两个进程的输出是不同级别的，嗯，你可以看到它们都在键入“f”。
They're producing each byte of their
output at the same time as
the other process is producing the
corresponding bytes of its output,
so the output of the two processes are
inter league,
um, you can see that they're both typing "f".
嗯，他们两个都会输入Fork Return。
Um, they're both gonna type fork return.
嗯，所以你可以从两个字母中看到“f”，在字母“o”中可以看到，在字母“r”中也可以看到，以此类推。
Um, so you can see the "f"
from both of them, in the
"o" both of them and the
"r" both and so on.
嗯，其中之一。
Um, one of them.
嗯，你可以看到那1行末尾的0在子分叉返回值0中。
Um, you can see the 0 at the
end of that 1 line is in
the child fork return 0.
嗯，我猜父叉应该返回19。
Um, I'm guessing that the parent fork return 19.
也就是说，在xv6下，子进程的id是19，这基本上意味着自引导以来创建的19个进程。
That is the child's process id is
19, under xv6 that basically means the
19 process that was created since boot.
嗯，然后其中一个印上“孩子”，你可以看到“c”、“h”、“i”、“l”、“d”交错，另一个是准备的。
Um, and then one of them prints "child"
and you can see the "c" "h"
"i" "l" "d" interleave with that is
the other one prepare.
所以，是的。
So, yeah.
这是对fork的一种愚蠢的使用，但是我们可以在这个输出中生动地看到，它创建了两个进程，它们都在运行以返回这两个进程，并且它们都在运行。
This is a silly use of fork,
but we can see vividly in
this output that has created two
processes that are,
and both of them are running for
returning both processes and they're both running.
但还要注意一个打印子进程和另一个父进程，所以fork返回不同的Um和两个进程很重要。
But also note that one printed child
and the other parent so it's important
that fork returns differently
Um, and the two processes.
问题，嗯，作为派生结果的子进程是否总是与父进程相同，或者它们是否可能不同。
Question, um,
is the child process as a result of
fork always identical to the parent process
or could they be different.
嗯，在xv6中是一样的。
Um, in xv6 are identical.
嗯，除了来自fork的返回值。
Um, except the return value from fork.
你知道指令是一样的，数据是一样的，堆栈是一样的，嗯，也都一样。
You know the instructions are the same
that data is the same,
the stack is the same,
um, also both.
进程，处理器复制，它们都有各自独立的地址空间，也就是说，它们都有，它们都认为它们的内存从0开始，从那里往上走。
Processes, the processor copies and they both have
their own separate
address spaces that is they both
have they both think that their
memory starts at 0 and goes
on up from there.
嗯，但是不一样，是不同的不同的记忆。
Um, but it's different it's different different memory.
嗯，和他们两个一起。
Um, with the two of them.
在更复杂的操作系统中，有一些细节我们绝对不在乎，它们可能偶尔会导致父级和子级不同，但在xv6中，除了返回值之外，它们是相同的。
In a more sophisticated operating system,
there are some details which we definitely
don't care about them,
they may occasionally cause parent and child
to differ, but in xv6
they're the same except the return value.
嗯，所以内存是一样的，另外呢复制了这个文件描述符表。
Um, so the memory is the same,
in addition the, um,
file descriptor table is copied.
所以如果家长打开了一些文件。
So if the parent had some files open.
嗯，孩子看到的是同一组文件描述符。
Um, and the child sees the same set
of file descriptors.
嗯，虽然孩子看到的是复印件。
Um, although the child is seeing them in a copy.
文件描述符信息表的。
Of the table of file descriptor information.
所以我们稍后会看到，fork复制打开的文件描述符表和内存是非常重要的。
And so we'll see in a moment
that it's quite important that a fork
copies the table of open file descriptors
as well as the memory.
好的那么。
Okay so.
叉子创建了一个新的进程，但是当我们在shell中运行东西时，嗯。shell确实创建了一个新进程来运行您键入的每个命令。
A fork creates a new process,
but when we run stuff in the shell,
um. The shell indeed creates a new process
to run each command that you type.
嗯，但是它需要在其中实际运行命令，所以如果我输入ls，我们需要shell forks来创建一个进程来运行ls，但是需要有一些方法。
Um, but it needs to actually run the command in it,
so if I type ls,
we need to shell forks to create
a process to run ls,
but there needs to be some way.
对于这个新进程，实际运行ls程序中的指令。
For that new process actually run the
instructions from the ls program.
在名为ls的文件和示例程序中的指令下面，我将立即向你们展示。
Below those instructions from the file called
ls and the example program,
I'm gonna show you in a minute.
嗯，使用ECHO，ECHO是一个非常简单的命令，a只接受您传递给它的任何参数，并将它们写到它的输出中。
Um, uses echo, echo is a very
simple command a just takes whatever arguments
you pass to it and writes them
to its output.
我为你们准备了一个叫“EXEC”的节目。
And I prepared for you a program called 'exec'.
嗯，嗯。
Um, um.
这是一个运行，它进行exec系统调用，用从您指定的特定文件读取的指令替换调用进程。
Which a run which
makes the exec system call which replaces
the calling process with the instructions read
from a particular file
you specify.
在当前进程上加载该文件中的指令，或丢弃其当前内存，然后开始执行这些指令，因此对exec系统调用exec的调用在第12行。
Loads the instructions from that file over
the current process or discarding its current
memory and then starts executing those instructions,
so the call to exec system call
exec on line 12.
它将产生操作系统从名为echo的文件加载指令的效果。
It's going to have the effect of
the operating system loading the instructions from
the file called echo.
在当前进程中，类似于替换当前进程的内存，然后开始执行。
In the current process sort of replacing
the memory of the current process and
then starting to execute.
嗯，这些指令，还有，你可以传递参数，命令行参数，回显exec允许你传递一组命令行参数。
Um, those instructions and in addition,
you can pass arguments command line arguments
echo exec allows you to pass an
array of command line arguments.
它只是C行10中的一个指针数组，它建立了一个字符指针数组，它本质上是字符串，并将该数组初始化为，以包含字符串echo，这是echo，嗯。
It was just an array of
pointers in C line 10 sets
up an array of
character pointers which are essentially strings and
initialize that array to be,
to contain the strings echo, this is echo, um.
这等同于用它们和三个参数调用Running ECHO。
And that's equivalent to calling running echo
with them and with
the three arguments.
这是Echo，所以当我想要EXEC的时候。
This is echo and so when I want exec.
嗯，确实，嗯，我看到这个输出，这是echo，但是即使我运行了exec命令exec程序。
Um, indeed,
um I see this output,
this is echo,
but even though I ran the exec
command exec program.
exec程序所做的就是调用exec系统调用，将其自身替换为echo，因此它实际上就是echo程序。
What the exec program does is calling
the exec system call to replace itself
with echo and so it was really
the echo program.
我正在制作这个输出。
I'm producing this output.
关于exec系统调用，对我们来说很重要的一点是，exec保留了当前的文件描述符表，所以无论在exec之前引用了什么文件描述符0、1、2等，它们在这个新程序中引用的都是相同的东西，我们已经加载了它们的指令。
And something about the exec system call,
that's important for us is that
it exec preserves the current
table of file descriptors,
so whatever file descriptor 0 1 2
etc, were referred to before exec,
they refer to the same thing in this new program
whose instructions we've loaded.
另外一点是，通常exec不会返回，因为exec完全取代了当前进程的内存，嗯，exec没有什么可以返回给exec的。
Another point is that ordinarily exec does
not return because exec replaces
the current processes memory entirely,
um, there's nothing for exec to return to
exec you know.
读取该文件的指令并执行它们，然后，嗯，exec唯一转到的时候是，如果发生了一些错误，导致操作系统无法为您运行该程序，例如，如果该程序根本不存在。
Read the instructions for that file and
execute them and then that's it,
um, the only time exec turns
is if some error occurred that
prevented the operating system from running
that program for you,
so for example if the program doesn't
exist at all.
EXEC找不到名为ECHO的文件，例如EXEC将返回-1。
Exec can't find a file called echo,
for example an exec would return -1.
嗯，表示出了一些错误，它找不到文件，所以普通的exec不会返回。
Um, Signal that something wrong it couldn't
couldn't find the file so ordinarily
exec does not return.
只有当内核不能实际为您运行该文件时，它才会返回。
It only returns if the kernel
couldn't actually run the file for you.
关于高管的问题。
Questions about exec.
聊天中的问题是argv中的最后一个0是什么。
The question in the chat is
what is the last 0 for
in argv.
它标志着数组C的结尾是如此之低，以至于，嗯，没有C数组方案。
It marks the end of the array
C is so low level that,
um, there's no
the C array scheme.
没有办法让代码找出数组的长度，所以告诉内核，嗯，你知道我们在数组中遇到的Echo，这是Echo，仅此而已。
Doesn't have a way for
code to find out how long
the array is and so
tell the kernel that,
um, you know we met at the array contains echo,
this is echo and nothing more.
我们把0作为最后一个指针放在最后一个条带上。这些双引号中的每个字符串实际上都是指向包含这些字节的某些内存的指针。
We put zero was the last strip as the last
pointer. Each of those strings in double quotes
is actually a pointer to some memory
that contains those bytes.
数组的第五个元素是指针值为0，惯例是指针值为0的指针或所谓的空指针。
That fifth element of the array is
a pointer's value is 0,
the convention is that a pointer
whose value is 0 or what's
called a null pointer.
嗯，这没什么意义，嗯，有了它。
Um, sort of signifies nothing,
Um, with it.
您已经离开了，所以内核中的代码实际上已经遍历了这个数组，直到找到它为止。
You were gone,
so the code in the kernel
has actually walks through this array
until it finds it.
值为零的元素。
Element whose value is zero.
好的，嗯，好的，这就是程序如何自我替换。
Okay, um,
all right,
so this is how a program can replace itself.
使用文件中的另一个程序，但实际上当我们在shell中运行诸如‘echo abc’、um或ls或其他任何东西时，我们不想替换shell，我们没有shell，只需调用exec即可。
With another program from a file,
but actually when we run stuff in
the shell like 'echo abc',
um or ls or anything else,
we don't want to replace the shell,
we don't have a shell,
just call exec.
嗯，因为这会用echo命令替换shell，然后echo退出。
Um, because,
that would replace the shell with the
echo command then echo exited.
那就结束了，你知道我们不想要回声来代替贝壳，所以贝壳实际上是分叉的。
That would be end, you know
we don't want an echo to
replace the shell,
so the shell actually does is fork.
然后孩子调用exec，这是一个非常常见的Unix惯用程序。
And then the child calls exec
and that's an extremely common unix
idiom program instead.
嗯，想要运行一个程序，但是重新获得控制权，他们所做的就是叫fork，让孩子叫exec。
Um, want to run a program,
but regain control what they do
is call fork and have the
child called exec.
这里有一个简单的例子，这个forkexec程序。
So here's a simple example,
this forkexec program.
在这个程序中，调用fork行12，在子行14中，我们调用exec，与前面非常相似。
In this program call fork line 12
in the child sort of line 14
we call exec much like before.
子进程，嗯，必须用echo命令替换它自己。
The child process,
um, has to replace itself with the echo command.
嗯，Echo，做完这件事，然后退出。
Um, echo,
does this thing and then exits.
然后父进程重新获得控制权，因为嗯，当fork返回时。
And then the parent process,
regains control because um when fork returns.
父进程中的值大于零值，所以父进程在19继续执行，Unix提供一个等待系统调用行24的进程来等待用fork创建的子进程，因为当我在命令行上运行命令时。
Greater than zero value in the parent process,
so the parent process then continues to
execute at 19 and unix provides a
wait system call line 24 process to
wait for child that created
with fork, because when I run a
command on the command line.
我们希望shell在再次打印提示符之前等待命令完成，然后再打印$PROMPT，要求我输入更多信息。
We want shell to wait for the
command to finish before it prints the
prompt again, before it prints is $
prompt asking me for more input.
所以，等待系统调用允许进程等待它的任何子代返回，这个状态参数是，嗯，退出子代的一种方式，将一个整数32位值，从退出的子代传递给第17行上等待的父代，退出的参数是1，这是退出的参数。，。
So it's the wait system call allows
a process to wait for any of
its children to return and this status
argument is that, um,
a way for
exiting child to communicate one integer
32 bit value from the exiting child
to the waiting parents on line 17 that
argument to exit that 1 that's the
argument to exit.
操作系统将其从退出的子级传递给等待行20的调用，因此等待&WAIT将状态变量的地址传递给内核，内核用，嗯，Child的参数填充该地址以退出。
The operating system passes that one from
the exiting child
to the call to wait line
20 so wait the & wait,
is passing the address of the
status variable to the kernel,
the kernel fills in that address with,
um, child's argument to exit.
Unix中的约定是，如果程序成功完成，退出时状态为0。
And the convention in unix is that
if a program completes successfully exit exits
with status 0.
嗯，但是它在第17行遇到了一个错误。
Um, but it has encountered an error at line 17.
嗯，Unix的惯例是您传递1来退出，所以如果您在意的话，调用进程可以查看WAIT的状态。
Um, the unix convention is that you
pass 1 to exit and so if
you care the calling process can look
at the status from wait.
确定孩子是否成功完成。莫里斯教授的一个快速问题。
Decide whether the
child completed successfully. A professor
Morris quick question.
对，关于exec call 19，嗯，我们刚才提到，exec将完全进入echo程序，不会返回fork exec。
Yes, about the exec call 19, um,
we mentioned not a bit ago that
exec will completely go into the echo
program and not return to fork exec.
嗯，所以，哦，会不会到16号线和17号线。
Um, so,
oh, would ever reach line 16 and 17.
不适用于这段EXEC代码，因为恰好有一个名为ECHO的程序，但是如果我在这里修改该代码，让我只修改这段代码。
Well, not for this exec code because there
happens to be a program called echo,
but if I modify that code here,
let me just modify this code.
好的，那么首先让我运行一下forkexec。
Okay, so first let me just
run forkexec.
它实际上使用我们看到的输出“this is echo”这些参数执行echo，并且我们看到子级退出，以显示ECHO成功退出，父级在等待。让我为您修改一下程序。
It actually does execute echo with those
arguments we see the output,
"this is echo" and we see
the child exited to show that
echo exited successfully and the parent wait
for. Let me just
modify the program for you.
嗯，而不是ECHO要运行一些不存在的命令。
Um, instead of echo going to run some
command that doesn't exist.
嗯，嗯，实际上是QEMU的出口。用‘Ctrl-ax’，然后重新编译整个东西，以便重新编译，我修改了。
Um, um,
actually the exit out of
QEMU. With 'Ctrl-a x' and then rebuild
the whole thing in order to re-compile
I modified.
Forkexec现在修改后再次运行forkexec。
Forkexec now run forkexec back again
after modifying it.
这一次，因为我们要求执行的程序，嗯，实际上，我们要求执行的程序不存在，EXEC确实返回了，我们看到EXEC失败的输出。
And this time because the program
we're asking to,
um, actually,
the program,
we're asking to execute doesn't exist,
exec does return we see the exec failed output.
嗯，出口1，你会看到那里的1被传回给家长，说孩子退出了状态。
Um, and the exit 1 you'll see
the 1 there is communicated back
to the parent which says the
child exited the status 1.
因此，当出现错误时，exec返回到调用函数。
So exec returns back to the calling
function when something went wrong.
是。嗯。
Yes. Yeah.
好的很好。
Okay good.
好的，嗯，这里要注意的是，实际上你们中的许多人已经注意到了。
All right,
um, something that going to note
here that actually think many of you
already noted is that.
这在这里是一个常见的习惯用法，这个派生后面紧跟着子进程中的exec，派生复制整个父进程可能有点浪费。
It is a common idiom here,
this fork followed by exec in the
child and it's potentially a bit wasteful
the fork copies the entire parent process.
但是exec会丢弃所有复制的内存，并将其替换为，嗯，您正在运行的文件中的任何内容，所以您知道您是否担心这种东西，即分支所暗示的副本。
But exec throws away all that copied
memory and replaces it with,
whatever is in the, um,
a file that you're running,
so you know if you're worried about
this kind of stuff,
the copy implied by the fork.
在某种意义上大部分是浪费的，因为所有复制的内存都被丢弃，并由EXEC替换。
Is in some sense mostly wasted because
all that copied memory is just thrown
away and replaced by the exec.
如果你有一个调用fork的几千兆字节的程序，这实际上对大程序的影响是很大的。
And this affects actually would be significant
for big programs,
if you have a multi gigabyte program
that calls fork.
嗯，而且它确实复制了所有的内存，实际上可能只需要不到一秒钟的时间来复制。
Um, and it did indeed copy all
the memory would actually take a
fair fraction of a second perhaps
to do the copy.
嗯，这可能是个问题。
Um, which could be a problem.
嗯，嗯，但是在本课程的后面，您将实际实现一些优化，特别是所谓的写入时复制派生，它将消除几乎所有明显的低效派生复制，只会让exec丢弃该副本。
Um, um,
but later in the course you'll actually
implement some optimization in particular something called
copy-on-write fork which will eliminate
almost all of the apparent inefficiency
of fork copying only to have exec
throw away the copy.
事实证明，它使用了一系列涉及虚拟内存系统的技巧。
It turns out with a bunch of
tricks involving a virtual memory system.
嗯，你可以构建一个分支，这对于拷贝来说是懒惰的，在通常的情况下，分支后面紧跟着exec，不会这样做。
Um, you can build a fork,
that's lazy about the copy and that
doesn't do in the common case of
fork immediately followed by exec.
嗯，或者你实际上不需要复印，因为孩子实际上并没有使用大部分的内存。
Um, or you don't actually have to do
the copy because the child doesn't actually
use most of the memory.
嗯，我想你会发现那是个有趣的实验室。聊天中的问题，为什么父进程父进程在子进程调用EXEC之前完全等待。
Um, I think you'll find that's a fun
and interesting lab. Question from chat,
why does the parent process parent waiting
completely before the child calls exec.
嗯。这只是偶然。
Yeah. It's just chance.
嗯，为什么你知道观察结果是，嗯，你知道。
Um, why is it that you know the observation is that,
um, you know.
嗯，可能是父母的输出和孩子的输出可以交错在我们以前看到的类似叉子例子的同一个区域，嗯，只是不能保证这就是输出，我们会看到实际上我们，我们看到输出的行是另一种顺序或者交错的，我们应该不会感到惊讶。
Um, it could be that the parents output
could be interleaved with the child's output
in the same area that we saw
before with similar fork example,
um, it just happens not to be there's
no guarantee that this is the output,
we would see in fact we,
we shouldn't be surprised if we saw
the lines of the output in the
other order or interleaved.
我怀疑到底是怎么回事，这需要一点时间和精力。
I suspect what's going on, is
that it takes a bit of
time and effort.
exec系统造成了一些开销，因为它必须加载所有需要访问文件系统和磁盘的内容，并在分配了一些内存之后，将名为echo的文件的内容从磁盘读取到内存中，而且即使在从旧进程中释放了一些内存之后，exec系统调用也需要相当多的机器，嗯。显然，这需要足够长的时间，父母才能完成输出。
The exec system caused a little bit
expensive, because it has to load all
those you have to access the file
system and access the disk and read
the contents of a file called echo
off the disk into memory,
after allocating some memory and
that even after freeing some memory
from the old process so there's
quite a bit of machinery involved
in the exec system call,
um. And apparently that takes long enough that
the parent can complete producing the output.
在EXEC完成并开始运行ECHO之前。
Before the exec is finished and
started running echo.
这有意义吗。
Does that make sense.
另一个问题是孩子不能等父母的习俗。
Another question is a convention that the
child can't wait for the parent.
Unix不可能没有办法满足孩子们的需求。
There's not a way unix doesn't have
a way for the child.
对于孩子来说，没有直接的方式等待父母的到来。
There's no straightforward way for a child to wait
from a parent.
等待系统调用。
The wait system call.
因为这是唯一可用的机制，所以等待系统调用会等待您的孩子。
Because it's the only mechanism available
well the wait system call waits
for your children.
就这样了。
And that's it.
所以等待所做的就是，嗯，如果你有孩子的话。
And so what wait what wait does is,
um, if you have any children.
他们中的一个已经离开了正在退出的地方。
And one of them has already exited what does exit.
然后我们会回来，但是你知道，如果你没有孩子，那就说，因为你有。
Then we will return but you know
if you don't have any children say,
because you are.
因为在这个简单的情况下，嗯。如果孩子打电话给WAIT，那就只有父母和孩子了。
Because in this simple case,
um. It was just a parent and child
if the child called wait.
该子进程没有任何子级，在这种情况下，WAIT只是立即返回，并返回-1错误，说明该进程没有任何子级。
The child doesn't have any children and
in that case,
wait just returns immediately with a -1
error return saying this process doesn't
have any children.
无论如何，简短的答案是，孩子没有办法等待它的父母离开。
Anyway, the short answer is there's no way
for a child to wait for its
parent to exit.
另一个问题是，当我们说孩子复制了父进程的所有内存时，我们到底指的是什么，我认为孩子会再次定义变量。
And another question when we say
the child copies all the memory
from the parent process,
what exactly do we refer to by
that I thought the child is going
to define the variables again.
嗯，或者当你编辑这个的时候，你知道，嗯。编译后，您的C程序。
Um, or when you compile this,
you know,
um. After compilation,
your C program.
它只是内存中的一堆指令，它们驻留在RAM中。
It's just a bunch of instructions in
memory that live in ram.
嗯，所以那些是可以复制的。
Um, and so those can be copied.
因为它们只是存在于RAM中的字节，可以复制到其他地方，嗯。以及与设置有关的适当技巧。
Because they're just bytes living in ram,
those can be copied somewhere else,
um. And with appropriate trick having to do
with setting up.
一种虚拟内存映射，并使子进程和父进程中的映射看起来是一样的，您只需将父进程的内存映像复制到子进程并执行子进程即可。
A sort of virtual memory mapping's and
make map things look the same in
the child and the parent you can
just copy the parent's memory image to
the child and
executing the child.
即使我们在看C程序，你也应该把它们看作是一堆机器指令。
And even though we're looking at C programs,
you should think of them as just
a bunch of machine instructions.
嗯，这是内存中可以复制的字节。
Um, which is bytes in memory that can be copied.
如果父级有多个子级，只要等第一个子级完成就返回，这意味着可能会有更多与父级和未完成的子级交织在一起，他们需要多种不同的方式来确保所有子级都完成。
If a parent has multiple
children would wait just return
as soon as the first
child finishes meaning that there
could be some more interleaving
with the parent and unfinished
children with their need to
be multiple separate ways to
ensure all children finished.
是的，如果您调用一个以上的fork(如果给定的进程调用两次)。
Yes, yeah,
if you call fork more than one
if a given process calls for twice.
嗯，那两个孩子都要等，每个电话要等两次。
Um, then it wants to wait for both
children and has to call wait twice
each call to wait.
当等待返回时，您不一定知道退出的是哪个子进程，权重将返回子进程的进程id作为返回值，这样您就可以知道了。
Will return as soon as one of
the children exits you don't when wait
returns you don't necessarily know which child
is exited the weight returns the child's
process id as its return value so
you can tell.
等我们回来后，你就知道是在哪一个出口了。
After we returns you know which one
it was at exit.
嗯，最后举一个例子，嗯。我想给大家展示一下，嗯，这些设施是怎么结合的，嗯。来实现IO方向，所以如果您还记得，嗯，shell为我们提供了这个方便的语法，我可以说‘echo hello>out’。
Um, as a final example,
um. I'd like to show,
um, how all these facilities combine,
um. To implement IO direction,
so if you remember,
um, the shell provides us with this
handy syntax I can say
'echo hello >  out'.
嗯，这就运行了回显命令，这个参数发送它。
Um, that runs the echo command that
argument sending it.
首先，嗯，这会把它的输出发送到文件中，然后向外看。
First, um, that sends its output to the
file out and looked out.
或者现在还没有。
Or yet.
嗯，在cat上，在其输入从out文件连接的情况下，我们可以看到echo命令保存的输出。
Um, on the cat and with its
input connected from the out file,
we can see that saved output from
the echo command.
嗯，贝壳设置的方式。
Um, the way the shell sets this up.
这个是，嗯，如下所示。
Um is,
um, as follows.
恩。如果shell首先像第13行那样分叉，然后在子程序中，shell更改文件描述符的设置方式，以致子程序的文件描述符1，按照惯例大多数程序都用于输出，嗯。这个shell a将子shell的文件描述符更改为1以引用此输出文件，然后运行您想要的任何命令，这会使父shell文件描述符1保持不变，因此这种派生和在子shell中围绕文件描述符进行更改的习惯用法。
Um. It a shell first forks like on
line 13 and then in the child,
the shell changes the way the file
descriptors are set up so that the
child's file descriptor
1 which
by convention most programs used for the output,
um. This shell a changes the child's
file descriptor to 1 to refer
to this output file,
and then run whatever commands you wanted
and that leaves the parent shells file
descriptor 1 unchanged so this idiom of
forking and in a child, changing
around the file descriptors.
Unix通常会将您运行的命令的输入和输出重定向，但不会影响调用程序的输入和输出，因为我们不想重定向shell的输出。
Um, is the usual way unix actually redirect
input an output for a command
that you run but not affect
the input and output for a
calling program because we don't want
to redirect the shell's output.
嗯，我们只想重定向子程序的输出。
Um, we only want to redirect the
child programs output.
不管怎样，这种工作方式我们称之为fork不寻常的方式，第15行只在子级中执行。
Anyway, the way this works we call fork unusual way,
a line 15 only executes in the child.
第15行上关闭1的原因是在此程序中。
The reason for the close 1 on
line 15 is that in this program.
我们重定向的只是echo命令的输出，所以当我运行这个重定向时。
We're redirecting a just the output of
the echo command,
so when I run this redirect.
程序本身不会产生输出，它会将其输出直接运行到“output.txt”。
A program produces no output itself,
it ran echo with its output directly
to "output.txt".
所以当我看到“output.txt”时，嗯。我看到了这个预期的输出，也就是第15行关闭1的原因。
So when I look at "output.txt",
um. I see this expected output,
the reason for the close 1 on line 15.
我们希望1作为一种常规的输出文件脚本来引用其他内容，所以我们没有子级，我们不想使用shell中连接到控制台的父描述符1。
Is that we want 1 as
a sort of conventional output file script
to refer to something else,
it happens so we don't have a child,
we don't want to use the father descriptor
1 that the shell had that's connected
to the console.
嗯，第16行上对open的调用保证返回1，因为open的语义是open返回最低的文件描述符编号，因为我们刚刚关闭了1，所以调用过程中当前没有使用这个编号。
Um the call to open on line
16 is guaranteed to return 1 because,
um the semantics of open are that
open returns the lowest
file descriptor number,
that's not currently in use in the
calling process since we just closed 1.
我的意思是，文件描述符0仍然连接到控制台。
And file descriptor 0 is still connected
to the console,
I mean.
我是开放的，保证返回1。
I'm open is guaranteed to return 1.
因此，在第16行文件描述符1连接到该文件之后。
So after the line 16 file descriptor
1 is connected to this file.
当我们执行ECHO时，ECHO只是写入它的输出，文件描述符1，现在转到这个文件，最酷的是，ECHO不知道发生了什么，ECHO根本不需要知道IO方向，它只写入它的输出，文件描述符1。
When we exec echo, echo just writes its output,
the file descriptor 1 and now go
to this file and the cool thing
about this is echo had no idea
what's going on, echo doesn't need to
know about IO direction at all,
it just writes its output,
the file descriptor 1.
我是唯一知道IO重定向的外壳。
I'm only the shell
knows about
IO redirection.
这个示例还说明了fork和exec之间的一种巧妙分离，即fork和exec我们单独的系统调用是分开的。
This example also illustrates the sort of
kind of neatness of the separation between
fork and exec, the fact that fork
and exec our separate system calls separate.
嗯功能。
Um functions.
意味着孩子在分叉之间有一段时间。
Means that there's a period of time
in the child between the fork.
在它们之间查找子进程中的返回值和确切的哪些仍在运行调用进程的指令，因此调用进程。
Between them for returns in the child
and exactly which were still running the
calling processes instructions,
so the calling process.
即使它在子进程中运行，在子进程中运行的指令仍然是调用进程指令执行的，因此调用进程仍然能够进行更改，并且在第19行之前仍然处于控制状态。
Even though it's running in those instructions
are running in the child,
it's still the calling processes instructions that
are executed and so the calling process
is still able to change things and
still in control up until line 19.
fork和exec之间的这种间隔使该节目有机会更改文件描述符(例如，引用的内容)。
And this sort of interval between fork
and exec gives the show a chance
to change what the file descriptors,
refer to for example.
有关此重定向示例的任何问题。
Any questions about this redirect example.
嗯。好了，我快没时间了。
Yeah. All right, I'm about out of time.
总结一下，我们来看看Unix是，嗯。Unix的IO和进程抽象的一堆接口，嗯，如果接口相对简单，只是在它的参数系统调用之间来回传递像文件描述符和进程ID这样的整数，嗯。但是，接口内的功能相对复杂，比如创建新进程和复制当前进程，此外，我还展示了一些单独简单的抽象如何以有用的方式组合在一起的示例，例如，生成IO重定向。
Just wrap up, we look at unix is,
um. A bunch of the interfaces to
unix's IO and process abstractions, um,
thing to take away from this is
if the interfaces are relatively simple and
just pass integer like file descriptors
and process ids back and forth across
its arguments system calls,
um. But,
Well, the functionality inside the interface is
relatively sophisticated like
creating new processes and copying the current
process, and furthermore I show some examples
of ways in which the abstractions
individually simple combine in useful ways,
for example to produce
IO redirection.
下周末将有一个实验，该实验涉及编写更多简单的实用程序，就像我展示的那些使用我们讨论的系统调用的实用程序。
There's a lab due at the end
of next week and that lab involves
writing more simple utilities like the ones
I showed that use the system calls
that we discuss.
所以，祝你在实验室玩得开心，下周课堂上见。
So, have fun with that lab and I'll
see you in class next week.
嗯，仅此而已。
Um, and that's it.
谢谢。
Thank you.
既然我是录音的人，那么我该怎么结束呢，第一次在课堂上录音。他们将会离开。
Since I'm the one recording,
how do I end this, first
time recording in lecture. They
will be exit.
好的，没什么特别的我可以直接退出它会被保存在某个地方。
Okay, nothing special I can just exit it
will be saved somewhere.
是的，太棒了。
Yes, awesome.
我假设我们将创建一些目录，并在该目录中粘贴一个文件。
I assume we'll create some directory and
sticking a file in that directory.
右转之后还有办公时间。
There's also office hours right after this right.
是的，太酷了。
Yes, perfect cool.
高兴的。好的。
Happy. All right.
All right,
好的，谢谢，下周见，谢谢。
thank you and I'll see you next week,
thanks.